<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine Learning on Aadithya's AI blog</title><link>https://aadithyakk.github.io/categories/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Machine Learning on Aadithya's AI blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aadithyakk.github.io/categories/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hash and Modulo Split Method: A Deterministic Alternative to Random Splits</title><link>https://aadithyakk.github.io/p/hash-and-modulo-split-method/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aadithyakk.github.io/p/hash-and-modulo-split-method/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aadithyakk.github.io/p/hash-and-modulo-split-method/sha-256.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Hash and Modulo Split Method: A Deterministic Alternative to Random Splits" />&lt;p>In machine learning, dataset splitting is an essential step to evaluate model performance. Traditionally, random splitting is widely used — especially with tools like &lt;code>scikit-learn&lt;/code> where you can just set a random seed to ensure reproducibility. However, there&amp;rsquo;s another method that provides even more control and consistency: the &lt;strong>hash and modulo split method&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we’ll dive into the details of how this method works, why it can be useful compared to traditional random splitting with a fixed seed, and explore scenarios where it can shine.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-traditional-approach-random-splitting-with-a-seed">The Traditional Approach: Random Splitting with a Seed
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Most machine learning practitioners are familiar with random splitting, where you randomly divide your data into training and testing sets (or training, validation, and testing sets). Tools like &lt;code>scikit-learn&lt;/code> make this easy. You can simply use the &lt;code>train_test_split()&lt;/code> function and provide a random seed for reproducibility:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-python" data-lang="python">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kn">from&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">sklearn.model_selection&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kn">import&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">train_test_split&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1"># Example of using train_test_split with a random seed&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">X_train&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">X_test&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">y_train&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">y_test&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">train_test_split&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">X&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">test_size&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mf">0.2&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">random_state&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">42&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>By specifying &lt;code>random_state=42&lt;/code>, you ensure that every time the code is run, the same split is produced. This allows for reproducible results, which is critical when you want to debug models or share results with others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="issues-with-random-seed-based-splitting">Issues with Random Seed-Based Splitting
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>While setting a random seed provides a level of consistency, it still has some drawbacks:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Requires Storage of the Seed&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
If the seed is not stored or is lost, the split can no longer be reproduced exactly. This can happen when working across different teams or machines. Even with a seed, future experiments may need an entirely new split.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Potential for Data Leakage&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
Random splitting could inadvertently lead to &lt;strong>data leakage&lt;/strong> when data from the same user, session, or time period appears in both the training and testing sets. This is particularly problematic in scenarios where there’s a temporal or user-related structure in the data.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Different Splits for Different Versions of the Data&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
If your data changes frequently (e.g., new users being added), the random seed will generate a different split every time the dataset is updated. This can make comparisons between different iterations of a model challenging.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This is where the &lt;strong>hash and modulo split method&lt;/strong> can come into play.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-hash-and-modulo-split-method">What is the Hash and Modulo Split Method?
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The hash and modulo split method provides a deterministic way to split a dataset based on a &lt;strong>unique identifier&lt;/strong> for each data point. This method is especially useful for datasets with inherent structures, such as user-based data, session-based data, or any scenario where reproducibility without randomness is desired.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-by-step-explanation">Step-by-Step Explanation
&lt;/h3>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Choose a Unique Identifier&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
Each data point in your dataset must have a unique identifier. This could be a user ID, session ID, or row index, depending on your dataset. The uniqueness is essential to ensure that the same data point will always be hashed to the same value.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Hash the Identifier&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
A hash function, such as &lt;code>SHA-256&lt;/code>, is applied to the unique identifier. The hash function converts the identifier into a fixed-size string or integer. Importantly, hash functions are &lt;strong>deterministic&lt;/strong>, meaning that the same input will always produce the same output.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Apply Modulo Operation&lt;/strong>:&lt;br>
Once the identifier has been hashed, the result is passed through a &lt;strong>modulo operation&lt;/strong>. The modulo operation divides the hash value by a number (say, &lt;code>N&lt;/code>) and returns the remainder. This remainder is used to assign the data point to either the training or testing set. For example, if you want an 80/20 split, you could use &lt;code>hash(id) % 5&lt;/code> — data points where the remainder is &lt;code>0&lt;/code> go to the test set (20%), while all others go to the training set (80%).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="example-implementation">Example Implementation
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Here’s an example of how this method can be implemented in Python using the &lt;code>hashlib&lt;/code> library:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt"> 1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 9
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">10
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">11
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">12
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">13
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">14
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">15
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">16
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">17
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-python" data-lang="python">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kn">import&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">hashlib&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1"># Function to hash a unique identifier and split based on modulo&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">def&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">hash_and_modulo_split&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">unique_id&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">split_ratio&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mf">0.2&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">):&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="c1"># Create a SHA-256 hash of the identifier (e.g., user ID)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">hash_value&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nb">int&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">hashlib&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">sha256&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nb">str&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">unique_id&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">encode&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">())&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">hexdigest&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(),&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">16&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="c1"># Apply modulo operation to split (e.g., 80/20 split using modulo 5)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">hash_value&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">%&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">5&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">==&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;test&amp;#39;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1"># 20% chance&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">else&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;train&amp;#39;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1"># 80% chance&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1"># Example usage for a list of unique IDs&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">data_point_ids&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">101&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">102&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">103&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">104&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">105&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">]&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">splits&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">hash_and_modulo_split&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">dp_id&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">for&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">dp_id&lt;/span> &lt;span class="ow">in&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">data_point_ids&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">]&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nb">print&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">splits&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>This approach ensures that every time you run the code, the split is consistent, as the hash of each identifier will always yield the same result.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-prefer-hash-and-modulo-over-random-seeds">Why Prefer Hash and Modulo Over Random Seeds?
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>While random seed-based splitting is convenient and effective, there are certain cases where the hash and modulo method offers significant advantages.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-perfect-reproducibility-across-data-changes">1. &lt;strong>Perfect Reproducibility Across Data Changes&lt;/strong>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>When using random splitting, if the data changes (e.g., new rows are added), the split could change even with the same seed. This can lead to inconsistent model evaluations and comparisons. With hash and modulo splitting, &lt;strong>new data points&lt;/strong> will always get assigned based on their unique identifier, meaning the old data points will continue to fall into the same training or testing set, while only the new ones will be assigned accordingly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-prevention-of-data-leakage">2. &lt;strong>Prevention of Data Leakage&lt;/strong>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>In cases like time-series data, or data where certain rows are related (e.g., the same user appears multiple times), random splitting can lead to data leakage — where information in the training set is indirectly used in the test set. Hash and modulo methods can prevent this. For example, by hashing a user ID, all data for a single user will be consistently placed in either the training or testing set, ensuring there&amp;rsquo;s no overlap.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-scalability">3. &lt;strong>Scalability&lt;/strong>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>For very large datasets distributed across different systems, it’s difficult to maintain a shared random seed and state to ensure consistent splitting. Hash and modulo methods, on the other hand, are &lt;strong>stateless&lt;/strong> — they don’t require knowledge of the entire dataset. You can compute splits independently on different machines as long as you have access to the unique identifier and hashing method. This makes the approach scalable across distributed environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-no-need-for-seed-management">4. &lt;strong>No Need for Seed Management&lt;/strong>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>One of the headaches with random splitting is managing the seed. If you accidentally change or lose the seed, reproducibility is lost. Hash and modulo methods don’t require any seeds, as the split is purely based on the unique identifier of the data points, making it inherently reproducible and reducing operational complexity.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-control-over-split-proportions">5. &lt;strong>Control Over Split Proportions&lt;/strong>
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>With random seed-based methods, ensuring a perfectly balanced 80/20 split can sometimes be tricky, especially when your dataset size isn’t evenly divisible by 5. The hash and modulo method, however, guarantees that you can split exactly 80% of the data for training and 20% for testing (or any other ratio you choose).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="when-to-use-random-splitting">When to Use Random Splitting
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>That said, the hash and modulo split method isn’t always the best choice. In scenarios where:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Class Balancing&lt;/strong> is important: If you need a balanced distribution of classes between the training and test sets (especially in small datasets), random splitting can ensure better distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Small Datasets&lt;/strong>: For small datasets, randomness can be beneficial as it introduces more diversity in both the training and test sets.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The &lt;strong>hash and modulo split method&lt;/strong> is a powerful and deterministic alternative to random seed-based splitting, offering perfect reproducibility, prevention of data leakage, and scalability. If your dataset is large, structured, or if reproducibility is critical in the face of changing data, this method is worth considering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While random seed-based methods are still the go-to for many, the hash and modulo split method ensures that your model is trained and tested consistently, across different runs and data versions, without the need to manage seeds or worry about accidental data leakage.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>